any of these three countries can walk
away with gold China usbekistan Qatar
it's a really interesting Confluence of
factors that makes men's 102 kg weight
category stacked in a way that we rarely
see at Olympic Games the next time we
see kurov on the lifting platform I mean
that's going to be I mean all eyes on
deck for that one right like cuz if he
actually calls for the a 500 kg squat on
the bar I mean what what a record that
would be we live in a world with active
conflict on multiple continents right
now and of course it's going to impact
the Sporting Community and I think it's
important that we highlight some of
these sad sobering and tragic stories
along with the triumphs that we get to
cover on the platform because these are
real people with real multifaceted
lives hey folks welcome back to strength
weekly the weekly strength Roundup that
brings you everything you need to know
from around the barbell game and
probably some things you don't know I'm
David thomasw I'm joined by Phil
Blackman we're going to get right into
it first up power L here kov squats 490
kg raw in training inching him closer to
his goal of being the lightest man to
squat 500 kg raw we get into that we
also go lifter by lifter for a stacked
Chinese Olympic weightlifting team
roster heading into the 2024 Paris
Olympics and some sobering news
Ukrainian weightlifter and Olympic
veteran Alexander penko has passed away
during a rocket attack in the Ukrainian
Russian war we talk a little bit about
that get some reactions from folks close
to the Ukrainian weightlifting community
and we also talk about the estimated
number of athletes and coaches to have
perished in that conflict one that has
perhaps an outsize impact on the
Sporting Community Phil let's go right
into powerlifting Zahir has not competed
since
2019 uh some people thought he was
retired I thought he was retired one of
the most exciting athletes to watch in
strength game that guy brings the energy
every time he steps on the platform he's
clearly not done at about 125 kilos body
weight he wants to squat 500 Kilograms
which would not only be a record in that
body weight category all time it would
be like it would just be disrespecting
the record books at this point Phil tell
us about his most recent training lift
how is he looking so he's looking
exceptional he has definitely not
retired yet because we are on the cusp
of him joining an elite club of being
able to squat 500 kog and the the
biggest highlight to me of that the fact
that he's already this close in training
is that if he does it he would be the
first athlete to ever do it outside of
the super heavyweight class not only is
he the lightest ever but he's actually
not even in the heaviest weight category
he's a weight category below it and that
to me is the most significant factor of
like how strong these lifts have
actually been in training so his most
recent training lift is 490 kilograms
obviously 10 kg away from the 500 kg
threshold Phil only three lifters have
ever squatted 500 kg or more raw in
competition uh one name kind of at the
top of that list Dan Bell all-time world
record holder in in the total uh and a
much heavier athlete than Zahir all
these athletes heavier than Zahir so
let's just make that clear karov is the
only athlete outside of the super
heavyweight division to ever reach the
500 kilogram squat if he does it on a
competitive liping platform being in the
same conversation as the alltime Great
Dan Bell is you're that like you were in
Goat conversation at that point I mean
Zahir already has an incredible resume
but to add this Accolade to it at 125
kilos would be I I would argue one of
the biggest highlights on that resume
yeah and I I would argue it's it's one
of those marks that we never thought
we'd see in powerlifting or at least I
didn't think we'd see in powerlifting at
this point under the super heavyweight
category now he's stilled to do it on
the platform I do want to point out one
fun one fun thing in this progression
his 455 kilo warm-up squat would have
been a top 20 heaviest alltime squat on
a competitive Raw competitive power
lifting platform so like when your
warm-ups would in theory place you in
the top 20 alltime squats that we've
ever seen anyone do raw in poweron
competition you're getting into rarified
air let's just put it that way you are
very much an anomaly in the space once
you're doing those kinds of lifts uh
that early on in your session I mean the
next time we see karov on the lifting
platform I mean that's going to be I
mean all eyes on deck for that one right
like CU if he actually calls for the a
500 kilogram squat on the bar I mean
that that's early in the in the
competition so he would actually need to
also secure his bench press and his
deadlift but I mean he's a pro he's like
that's very little doubt that he would
bomb out but like I mean what what a
record that would be he just came back
five years after he last stepped on a PL
on a platform many folks thought he was
done including me and suddenly all eyes
are on him very quickly which is
extraordinarily impressive and obviously
he stayed in fantastic form Phil when is
the next time we might see him attempt
this 500 kilogram competition Squad so
his next show that we're aware of that
he's going to compete in is the romini
wellness experience show in romini Italy
on June 1st so mark your calendars June
first if he calls for 500 kilograms on
the bar you are not going to want to
miss him trying to ascend a weight we
have never seen before at that body
weight it will be a uh check mark a
checkpoint in powerlifting history if he
does it one thing to point out the the
Rini Wellness experience on June 1st it
is as far as we know a fitness and
lifting Expo we are actually not sure
what the sanctioning body is for the
powerlifting portion of that or if it is
going to be sanctioned now I want to be
clear here this has to be in sanctioned
competition from some governing body in
order for it to be considered an
all-time world record right so move on
to the world of weightlifting Paris
Olympics are coming up 2024 seems like
just yesterday we were in Tokyo although
it was 2021 technically the 2020
Olympics it gets
confusing China is sending six athlet
thetes in weightlifting to the Paris
Olympics the maximum number they can
send now does that seem like a small
group of weightlifters yes it does
because weightlifting has fewer spots at
the Olympics this year than it has had
in many decades certainly in our
lifetimes and that is due to all sorts
of issues the sport has had at the
international level from doping to
corruption it's a little bit of a slap
on the wrist uh at one point we thought
the parasonic might be the last time we
see weightlifting the Olympics turns out
weightlifting spot is secur for the Los
Angeles Olympics in 2028 which we like
and hopefully we'll start seeing those
athlete counts increase as the number of
slots available for Olympic
weightlifters at the Olympic Games
increases but anyway six six members of
the team three men three women that is a
full roster Phil who's leading off let's
start with the men who's leading off on
the men's side leab Bean men 61
kilograms now here's the thing about the
Chinese weightlifting team they're
sending a full roster of six athletes
but their roster beond these six
athletes are all gold level caliber
Olympic weightlifters so the fact that
they that these are the six that China
has decided to send to Paris is a Mark
that these are the one they think
they're going in and taking home six
gold and it's it's tough to bet against
that the joke has been in the past and
it's also there's a lot of truth to it
that the Chinese National weightlifting
competition is tougher than the Olympic
Games because China can only send so
many lifters to the Olympic Games and
their rosters are so deep in certain
body weight C categories that if they
sent you know three lifters in the you
know the men's 61 kilo category they
would they would all finish you know
they would finish gold silver bronze
right so the joke is that because there
are fewer Chinese lifters in some of
these body weight categories at the
Olympics it's actually less competitive
than Chinese Nationals which is
interesting lefa Bean 61 kilos this is a
bodyweight category uh that China has
you know this range and let's call
because the last few Olympic Cycles
we've had body weight class
restructuring right this has been a good
sweet spot for China there have been
some there have been some exceptions
right there have it's not like China has
won Gold in every single category
they've sent male athletes to at the
Olympic Games you know for the past 16
years but since 2008 it's been darn
close to that is what we'll say and this
is a bodyweight category where China has
certainly dominated Leaf haban uh has
certainly dominated Phil what are some
recent highlights or highlights from
Fab's career to help contextualize his
performance yes he's competed 12 times
internationally over the last 5 years
and he has won 11 of those 12 so if
you're talking about uh win rate
consistency I mean Stellar on that front
moving on the men 73 kilo category we
have X xong now uh she is recovering
from a back injury I was honestly a
little surprised to see him Nam to this
roster not surprised but like after we
caught wind of the back injury we were
like oh you know it's not guaranteed
that he makes the roster seems like
recovery from that back injury is going
well enough for team China to think he
can take the gold because China in these
weight categories especially in these
lighter and middle men's bodyweight
categories doesn't really send anyone
unless they think they can win right so
how are we looking for the men 73s for
the Chinese here yeah so uh she is him
getting the nod to go that signals to me
that they're confident that he has fully
recovered from his back injury and is
fully capable of the weights that are
expected in order to score a gold medal
again for the third time so I think that
like while we have to we obviously have
to contextualize the fact that he has
been recovering from a back injury going
into this event I don't think the team
sends him knowing how deep of a roster
that they have if they don't think he
can actually convert another gold in
2024 yes and just a great reminder their
F he is the two-time defending Olympic
champion he would join a a small but
growing list of weightlifters to
potentially win three gold medals in a
row uh one of those lifters his country
L aljun who will not be competing at
this games he did try and make his
fourth Olympic games uh but due to uh
doping test doping test positive was
basically disqualified from the running
so we will not see lose out if if you've
been hiding under a rock for the last
two years and you're expecting to see L
zun at the Olympics yet again you won't
this time that's kind of old news but
but worth an update in someone who at 73
kilograms uh you know in these body
weight categories again body weight
category restructuring 73 77 Etc L and
really dominated that weight class for
over a decade it seemed Phil the third
man representing China is in a body
weight category that the Chinese have
not traditionally dominated uh that is
the men's 102 category and Leu huan is
the Chinese representative now this is a
heavier body weight category than we've
seen the Chinese tend to send to the
Olympic Games this guy by the way his
nickname online in weightlifting forums
at least in Western weightlifting forums
is
gigachad and he is a who since 2022 has
bumped up several weight classes and has
performances to match Phil how has he
been looking uh over the last couple
years since 2022 Lou has moved up two
weight classes from 89 kilograms to 102
kilograms and he has made the podium on
all six of his International appearances
and he's claimed two out of three
inaugural World Records during that span
of time so expect him to face off
against a pair of 2020 Olympic Champions
who have also changed weight classes in
order to compete in 2024 in the one of
is usasan Akbar JV and qari mesoa we
have basically a bunch of lifters here a
trio of lifters who are looking poised
for the podium now they're not the only
ones who can be competitive here but
they are significantly better from what
we've seen recently than the others in
that weightlift in that body weight
category and it's again the rare
instance when you have two lifters who
are Olympic champions from the most
recent Olympics competing in the same
body weight category and only one lifter
can win old right so it's really
interesting how this has played out and
suddenly the 102s went from I got to be
honest in the past handful of years not
a terribly exciting category to me to
watch to perhaps the most exciting men's
category because on any given day any of
these three lifters any of these three
countries could walk away with gold
China us Pakistan Qatar right these
athletes have all performed well at the
international level two won gold medals
in
Tokyo it's a really interesting
Confluence of factors it makes men's 102
kgam weight category stacked in a way
that we rarely see at Olympic Games this
category seems to be the most uh
impacted by the adjustment of athlete
quota from the previous Olympics because
all of these athletes have had to move
from their original weight class which
is not featured at the competition into
a weight class that is and as such we're
seeing 102s get a huge bump from
previous years uh like you said of like
what to look forward to this time around
let's move over to the women huo GUI is
the competitor at the lightest women's
body weight category that will be
contested in Paris it's not the lightest
women's body weight category period but
again we are not going to see every iwf
recognized bodyweight category contested
in Paris so the lightest for the women
is going to be 49 kilos now
interestingly this is the weight
category that also features team USA's
Jordan De La Cruz who's been looking
very good on the platform recently she
is an Olympic veteran so uh certainly
has her sites set on a potential Podium
finish after bombing out in Tokyo but
you know the Chinese uh these lighter
women's body weight categories they
normally have them locked up it's worth
noting that team North Korea their
biggest International competition is not
going to be here which makes me think
that the Chinese athlete is certainly
the favorite in the 49 kilo category
Phil yeah I have to Echo that I think
that like the the North Korean team they
are the ones that have been posting the
numbers on the international platform
forms that could theoretically compete
with the numbers that the Chinese team
is putting up but because they're not
going to be at the Olympics this time
around it seems like this is more or
less a hard lock for the most part it
would be a title defense it is the
expectation if they do it
congratulations that's fantastic if they
don't that would be one of the biggest
upset articles we would expect to right
all right Phil who's up next for the
women so next up we have L shei Fang in
the women's 59 kilogram class she has
won four gold medals of her five
subsequent appearances throughout the
Paris qualification I think arguably
again the performance that we expect to
actually claim the gold at the end of
the day yeah she's got 80% gold hit rate
International competition over the last
few years uh I would say this is hardly
a lock look none of these are locks
right bomb outs exist right you got to
show up on the platform a lot can happen
I wouldn't call this as near a certain
thing as the women's 49 kilo category uh
but I would say she's certainly the
favorite and Phil who is the third and
final woman who will be representing
China at the 2024 Paris Olympic Games in
weightlifting we wouldn't be talking
about a Chinese weightlifting team if we
didn't talk about Lee wenwen in the
women's super heavyweight class uh she
is the Premier talent in this weight
category over the last handful of years
in the last five years we've seen winwin
compete 10 times in major competition
she has won all 10 of those she is the
world record holder across the board in
this body weight
category I have I have a lot of trouble
seeing her not winning this I really do
yeah this is where like you know our our
our our J ISM can only go so deep when
all of the the the data and stats show
that it's just we it's Lee wentw across
the board uh at at every metric like I
mean if you were to take your easiest uh
your easiest call on this on this roster
it's when when taking the gold again all
right well Phil let's move on we'll stay
in the world of weightlifting but move
on to some sad news Ukrainian
weightlifter and Olympic veteran
Alexander Peno has passed away according
to multiple sources he died in a rocket
attack during the Ukrainian Russian war
that is currently ongoing in Europe Phil
what details do we know uh about
Alexander's uh about Alexander's passing
here so we know that the multip the
multiple time European Champion he was
30 years old at the time of his passing
uh and some of the accolades that we
know uh along the way that he has uh
scored as he won two continental titles
for Ukraine he finished fourth in his
weight class at the 2016 Olympic Games
in Rio uh and he died fighting in the
Russian Ukraine war he was reportedly
killed in action as you said in a rocket
attack on May 5th that's the date that
has been confirmed by multiple sources I
think we should go down some of his
career highlights along the way because
he did have a stellar resume yes for for
sure uh a few I'll point out he finished
fourth of the 2015 World Championships
uh he finished first uh in the 2016
European championships fourth of the
Olympic Games in Rio in 2016 and he was
again European champion in 2017 Brian
Oliver a contributor to barbend covered
his death and actually uh got a quote
from an official within Ukraine's
Ministry of sport this is a very sad
loss Alexander loved weightlifting it
was his life he worked as a coach in
Kiev and wanted to compete again when
this war started he joined the army on
the first day now according to sources
penko was married but did not have
children our deepest sympathies go out
to peno's Widow his family friends loved
ones coaches teammates everyone impacted
by his passing in the Ukrainian and
broader European weightlifting
communities the
reality of international conflict is
that it impacts people in all walks of
life and we get to sit here and we get
to talk about weightlifting and we get
to talk about International competition
in a somewhat sanitized way Phil we get
to talk about this and it's all kind of
it's all sunshine and rabos right it's
all everyone getting along International
cooperation Etc that's not the reality
of geopolitics these days and I think
it's important for us to recognize
within the broader International
Community of strength Sports we get the
luxury of highlighting a lot of the good
but we live in a world with active
conflict on multiple continents right
now and of course it's going to impact
the Sporting Community and I think it's
important that
we highlight some of these sad sobering
and tragic stories along with the
triumphs that we get to cover on the
platform because these are real people
with real multifaceted lives this is not
the sort of story we we to see this is
not the sort of story that we' like to
report on because we don't like to see
these things happen but I think it's
important that we do Phil no one cares
what I have to say about geop politics
nor am I an expert but I think it's
important for us to recognize that
tragedies do happen and these are real
people with lives that extend beyond
their performance and how much weight
they lift we have seen this conflict
impact many of the sports that we cover
even Beyond weightlifting uh we saw
Alexi novakov uh right after the war
started when he competed in strongman
and he put up one of the most
inspirational performance we
performances we had ever seen to a
bronze medal finish at the world's
strongest man competition we knew that
he was competing under the charge of the
Ukrainian war in the background you know
and the fact that he wasn't there he was
also enlisted to help fight and he would
had permission to come and compete and
he was the star of that world's
strongest man competition because of the
pressure that he was under to deliver
for his country in a way that brought
awareness to the boots on the ground
there so the the way that sport is able
to translate some of the the tragic of
what we're what we see in international
conflict even when we're at a distance
from it here in the in the US uh being
able to see the athletes that we love to
cover that we love to watch have to
experience what's going on there and
bring bring it over here and translate
that a little bit for us to give us
perspective of of how critical
everything that's happening over there
is I think is immensely important that
we we cover and that we share and that
we we promote on the platform that we
have in the audience that is that is
watching and to give a sense of the
scale at which this conflict has
impacted Ukrainian athletes and
Ukrainian sporting culture according to
Ukraine's Ministry of sport as of late
February 2024 so this stat is outdated
we're months Beyond this around 443
Ukrainian athletes and coaches have died
during the conflict that's nearly 500
people and I'm I it's sad to say that
you know that stat is several months
outdated it's likely that they've
crossed that that threshold of 500
coaches and athletes in the Ukrainian
sporting system who have died during
this conflict so we don't really have a
an upbeat way to end strength weekly
this week but I think that as we prep
for Olympic coverage as we prep to cover
weightlifting at the 2024 Paris Olympics
it's important to note that
international
sport is not in this bubble it's not in
a protected you know snow globe
that gets to exist outside of broader
factors in the
world especially when it comes to
International athletes and competition I
I I think it's important for us to
recognize that so um our hearts go out
to you know palenko like I said his
family loved ones former training
Partners coaches and to the entire
Ukrainian Sporting Community right now
yeah we will be covering the 2024 Paris
Olympic games of course uh but there is
the backdrop behind those games and on
any intern competition where uh
countries from across the globe are
coming to compete together uh in sport
that there there will be the the
backdrop of those conflicts while that
competition is going on and uh to remain
aware of all that to uh you know keep
yourself updated on what's going on
during those conflicts I think is
immensely important even though we get a
reprieve of it so to speak while we're
watching the sports that we love to
watch and that we love to cover um it's
important to like not lose sight of
what's going on yeah and also just to be
clear this Olympic Games is happening in
Europe in Paris while there is active
war in Europe Eastern Europe it seems
far away but there is not peace on the
continent while the Olympic Games is
happening and and I think that is
something that's all too easy to lose
sight of and um we will this is a good
reminder for us as journalists as
broadcasters to not lose sight of that
so Phil thank you for joining me today
folks thanks for tuning in we'll be
bringing you more action from strength
weekly and from around the world of
strength next week week
[Music]